MCP sampling landed in Pantic AI last
week. Let's explain what it is and how
to use it. So I actually talked about
MCP sampling at AI engineer a few weeks
ago. This diagram kind of explains how
it works. So when we make a call to an
MCP server, that MCP server can make
calls to an LLM instead of having to but
instead of having to make those calls
directly, it can proxy them via the MCP
client, which means you don't have to
provision your servers with res with LLM
resources, etc. instead they can use the
LLM available on the client. Let's have
a look at what that looks like in Pance
AI. So here we have a very simple
example of an app using Panti.
So we have a bit of bit of code here to
configure observability with logfire.
Then we have uh an MCP server running
over standard IO. This is going to call
the generate SVG uh file as I'll show
you in a minute. We have our agent which
is going to use OpenAI 4.1 GBT 4.1.
And then this is the core of our
application where we're basically going
to run our MCP servers and then make a
request to the agent uh asking it to
create an image of a robot uh in a punk
style that should be pink. The point
here is that our generate SVG
MCP server is going to register one tool
with our agent which is called uh image
generator. This in turn is going to take
care of converting a subject and a style
into an SVG image. In particular, this
is the clever bit here
where our agent, our pilanti agent here
uses the model MCP sampling model which
has access to MCP context and therefore
can make an LLM call proxied through the
client. Um, and then we're going to
we'll save the image and return the
path. Uh, notably
Pantic AI automatically enables sampling
if it's run as a client. You can disable
it if you want. Let's go and run this
example and see what it looks like.
So, we see uh logs start to print out
and we come over here to log fire. We
can see requests ongoing. See our agent
running.
uh when GPT40 responds as it has done
now we should be able to see exactly
what happened. So you'll see here that
we have uh our outer agent run
uh which called the tool as we would
have expected and then that returned uh
details of the image that's been
generated. We can see pricing on this
but notably you see here we have
distributed tracing. So we see when we
make the tool call, it goes uh from the
client into the server, then back to the
client to make the call to GP40
um and ultimately finished and output um
a summary of what happened. And indeed,
we can go and have a look at the image
that generated. It's not great on this
occasion, but MCP sampling worked
correctly.